Guide to the Master of Fine Arts in Experimental and Documentary Arts collection, 2012-2020 RL.11067
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- MFA/EDA Theses, 2014
  - Creative Theses, 2014
    - Kelly, Caitlin Margaret, 2014, 19 items 1 box 18 black-and-white inkjet prints; 1 postcard 13 x 19 inches
      From the artist's description: " 'Please Call Me By My True Names' is a portraiture project with women living with HIV and AIDS throughout the United States. Each woman was photographed in her home or other space personal to her. Her surroundings are as much a part of the portrait. Each image is inscribed on the bottom of the photograph with her name, age, and date she was diagnosed HIV positive. No other information or story is given. This is an intentional choice by the artist in response to 'expected narratives' surrounding women living with HIV.
      The title of the work is derived from a poem of the same name by Thich Nhat Han."
      Biographical Note
      Caitlin Margaret Kelly (b. 1973) grew up in New England in a family full of women. She earned a BS in Journalism from Boston University in 1991, focusing on photojournalism. Kelly then spent the next 17 years of her life as a newspaper photojournalist, both as a staffer for various Southern California newspapers or as a freelancer. During that time she returned to school to complete an MA in Anthropology from California State University in 2002. After living and working internationally in Buenos Aires, Argentina for five years, Kelly returned to complete her MFA in Experimental and Documentary Arts at Duke University in 2014. Kelly continues to use her skills and knowledge of the news industry to address representation and perception through her artwork. She is currently the Director of the Power Plant Gallery at Duke University and a member of the Committee on Women in the Arts for the College Art Association (2015-2018).
      - Exhibition postcard (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - LaSonja Allen (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - Melissa Baker (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - Tammy Bellish (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - Dee Borrego (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - Dawna Edwards Watson (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - Myra Johnson (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - Patricia Kelly Wilks (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - Jackie Knight (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - Kristine Koffler (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - Angela Krebs (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - Dona Lackey (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - Priscilla McCarthy (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - Nancy Molock (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - Gracie Ortiz (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - Catherine Catjia Redfern (Box 18, Folder 4)
      - Debbie Smith (Box 18, Folder 4)
      - Patricia Wilder (Box 18, Folder 4)
      - Ann Wright (Box 18, Folder 4)
- MFA/EDA Theses, 2015
  Series contains Duke University Master of Fine Arts in Experimental Documentary Arts theses from the class of 2015. The projects are listed in two groups, Written Theses and Creative Theses, and within are listed in alphabetical order by the students' last names.
  - Written Theses, 2015
    This subseries contains the written theses submitted by the MFA EDA Class of 2015 whose work is part of this archive. Submission of projects to the archive is voluntary. Theses are typescripts unless otherwise noted; titles are included when known.
    - Canipe, Aaron, 2015 (Box 3)
      Between the Mountains/Plateau: Stories, dreams, pictures, and drawings from a life in the North Carolina piedmont
    - Cicanese, Matthew, 2015 (Box 3)
      The Evolution of Wonder
    - Fish, Tracy, 2015 (Box 3)
      Autogeography
    - Kipervaser, Anna, 2015 (Box 3)
      [of heart and tongue]
    - Kutnick, Aaron, 2015 (Box 3)
      docu{rithm}: algorithmic narration of human experience
    - Li, Haodong, 2015 (Box 3)
      The Encounter of Cultures
    - Lowrey, Ava, 2015 (Box 3)
      Mothers and Daughter
    - McKone, Jonna, 2015 (Box 3)
      When Things Crack Apart
    - Pilarski, Nicholas, 2015 (Box 3)
      I, Destini
    - Polish, Mendal Diana, 2015 (Box 3)
      Finding Home: Years that Ask and Years That Answer
    - Stanback, Windrose, 2015 (Box 12)
      Tracing Sycamore
    - Striegl, Libi Rose, 2015 (Box 12)
      Thesis titled "thoroughly known," printed on dot matrix pages attached to clipboard.
    - Taalman, Alina, 2015 (Box 12)
      Quiet Title
    - Yarolin, Grant, 2015 (Box 3)
      a form that knows its way around
  - Creative Theses, 2015
    Subseries contains the creative theses submitted by the MFA EDA Class of 2015. Artists' statements and abstracts are included when provided.
    - Canipe, Aaron, 2015
      Plateau by Aaron Canipe includes 20 photographic prints (color and black-and-white) in various sizes from the exhibition: 17x22, 11x17, 8x12, and 5x7. Includes a finished book project measuring 8.5" x 9.5" of 88 pages with (1) 7" flexi vinyl record from the series and featuring various ephemera and promotional items that coincide, and the book's maquette completed before the final printing. In addition are (3) 11x17 risograph posters, (1) maquette of the book project, and (6) 8.5x11 documentations of the exhibition space at the Power Plant Gallery.
      Canipe provided the following abstract: "Plateau is documentation of the North Carolina piedmont told through various ways of seeing: through cell phone imagery, the view camera, and the lens of Thomas Wolfe's novella THE LOST BOY. These images were made during 2012-2015, in a number of counties through the state, as a part of the completion of the MFA in Experimental and Documentary Arts. The title, Plateau, refers a topographical feature found in the piedmont of North Carolina, between the mountain and coastal region of the state."
      - Plateau book, 2015 (Box 3)
      - 7 inch flexi vinyl disk, one-sided, of This World is Not My Home performed by Andrew Weathers, 2015 (Box 3)
      - Plateau book maquette, 2015 (Box 3)
      - Creek, Morganton, NC, 2015 (Box 10)
      - West End BBQ, Hickory, NC, 2014 (Box 10)
      - James and John, Raleigh, NC, 2014 (Box 10)
      - King's BBQ, Kinston, NC, 2014 (Box 10)
      - Grave of John Allen, Norlina, NC, 2014 (Box 11)
      - New Highway, Hickory, NC, 2014 (Box 10)
      - Tristan, Pittsboro, NC, 2014 (Box 10)
      - Superbowl Sunday, Mountain View, NC, 2012 (Box 10)
      - Stars, Kinston, NC, 2014 (Box 10)
      - Dr. Herb's Herbs, Hickory, NC, 2014 (Box 10)
      - Negative, Tobacco Queen, 2014 (Box 11)
      - Thornton-Hunter House, Yanceyville, NC, 2014 (Box 11)
      - Lost Dog, Plateau Road, Newton, NC, 2014 (Box 11)
      - I'm Lost, I'm Lost, Morganton, NC, 2013 (Box 11)
      - High School, Newton, NC, 2014 (Box 11)
      - Hearse, Graham, NC, 2014 (Box 10)
      - Barn Swallow, Hickory, NC, 2014 (Box 11)
      - Snake, Eden, NC, 2013 (Box 11)
      - Rufus, Durham, NC, 2013 (Box 10)
      - Scanned passage from The Lost Boy, 2015 (Box 11)
      - Risograph poster of Kudzu Jesus, Stigmata, Chik Fil A, fluorescent pink, 2015 (Box 10)
      - Risograph poster of Silk worm home/universe/does God really exist?, black, 2015 (Box 10)
      - Risograph poster of Thornton-Hunter House, blue, 2015 (Box 10)
      - Entrance view, Power Plant Gallery, 2015 (Box 11)
      - First wall view, Power Plant Gallery, 2015 (Box 11)
      - Second wall view, Power Plant Gallery, 2015 (Box 11)
      - Third wall view, Power Plant Gallery, 2015 (Box 11)
      - Text panel view, Power Plant Gallery, 2015 (Box 11)
      - Rear gallery view, Power Plant Gallery, 2015 (Box 11)
    - Fish, Tracy, 2015
      Tracy Fish's thesis Autogeography includes 32 color digital photographs taken between 2013 and 2015 printed on Epson Premium Luster 13"x19" photo paper and corresponding digital image files. In addition are digital images documenting solo exhibition at the Jameson Gallery in the Friedl Building of Duke University (2015).
      Fish provided the following abstract: "Autogeography is a personal observation that suggests both the ambiguity of place and interchangeability of landscape."
      If any material is used for research papers, please cite photographer. If possible, contact tsfishphotography@gmail.com so photographer can keep bibliography.
      - Raleigh, Wake County, North Carolina, 2014 (Box 10)
      - Seaside, Oregon, 2014 (Box 10)
      - Research Triangle Park, North Carolina, 2015 (Box 10)
      - Pleasant Hill, Missouri, 2014 (Box 10)
      - Diptych of Research Triangle Park, North Carolina and Pleasant Hill, Missouri, 2015 (Box 10)
      - Carolina Beach, North Carolina, 2015 (Box 10)
      - Lake Michigan, Loyola, Illinois, 2014 (Box 10)
      - Manzanita, Oregon, 2014 (Box 10)
      - Marine Park, Brooklyn, New York, 2013 (Box 10)
      - Jamaica Bay, Brooklyn, New York, 2013 (Box 10)
      - Roe Park, Overland Park, Kansas, 2014 (Box 10)
      - Diptych of Jamaica Bay, Brooklyn, New York and Roe Park, Overland Park, Kansas, 2014 (Box 10)
      - Jefferson City, Tennessee, 2015 (Box 10)
      - Paola, Kansas, 2014 (Box 10)
      - Georgetown, South Carolina, 2014 (Box 10)
      - Triptych of Jefferson City, Tennessee, Paola, Kansas, and Georgetown, South Carolina, 2014 (Box 10)
      - Hillsdale, Kansas, 2014 (Box 10)
      - Overland Park, Kansas, 2014 (Box 10)
      - Sheepshead Bay, Brooklyn, New York, 2013 (Box 10)
      - Aurora, Nebraska, 2014 (Box 10)
      - Canarsie, Brooklyn, New York, 2014 (Box 10)
      - Seagate, Brooklyn, New York, 2015 (Box 10)
      - Bergen Beach, Brooklyn, New York, 2014 (Box 10)
      - Pleasant Hill, Missouri, 2013 (Box 10)
      - Durham, North Carolina, 2015 (Box 10)
      - New Virginia, Iowa, 2014 (Box 10)
      - Diptych of Durham, North Carolina and New Virginia, Iowa, 2015 (Box 10)
      - Black River, North Carolina, 2014 (Box 10)
      - Orange City, Florida, 2013 (Box 10)
      - Diptych of Black River, North Carolina and Orange City, Florida, 2014 (Box 10)
      - Sunset Highway, Oregon, 2014 (Box 10)
      - Myrtle Beach, South Carolina, 2014 (Box 10)
      - Fish_Tracy_ADA_1 Images 1-19, Disk image derived from optical disc. 19 image files, approximately 2.3 gigabytes. (Box 3, Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0007)
      - Fish_Tracy_ADA_2 Images 20-32 Install at Jameson Gallery, Disk image derived from optical disc. 21 image files approximately 3.0 gigabytes. (Box 3, Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0007)
    - Kipervaser, Anna, 2015
      Contains materials from Kipervaser's thesis, titled "A deer hunt and no mistake." Includes the program of part one, in both print and PDF, as well as three videos which are representative of the program. The program premiered in March 2015 at the Full Frame Theater, Durham.
      1. Kipervaser_Golden-Racecar(s).mp4; .mp4 file of GOLDEN RACECAR(S), running 2 minutes and 15 seconds, color, sound.
      2. Kipervaser_Instrument.mp4; .mp4 file of INSTRUMENT, running 5 minutes and 50 seconds, color, sound.
      3. Kipervaser_He-Begins-She-Returns.mp4; .mp4 file of HE BEGINS, SHE RETURNS, running 2 minutes and 15 seconds, color, sound.
      Kipervaser provided the following abstract: "In addition to the PDF and printed versions of the program of A deer hunt and no mistake, the three experimental short moving image works included are described individually below.
      GOLDEN RACECAR(S): Inside out and counting. Plus.
      INSTRUMENT: Connecting time and place through undiscovered empty space between hemispheres. Shot in Indonesia, Hawaii, Alaska, Louisiana, and North Carolina – specifically at the History of Medicine Artifacts Collection, Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
      HE BEGINS, SHE RETURNS: It all ends in tears. And then."
      Only to be viewable on location at the Rubenstein Library, not downloadable, nor transferrable to any organization or individual. Not to be screened publicly outside of the library without prior consent from the artist.
      - A deer hunt and no mistake, 2015, Disk image derived from optical disc. 2 document files and 3 video files, approximately 2.3 gigabytes. (Box 3, Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0007)
      - Aziz and Vale, One video file (MP4 format) and a document file (Word format) describing it; approximately 0.1 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0007)
    - Li, Haodong, 2014-2015
      As a Matter of Things contains photographs taken by Haodong Li at Duke University and UNC, 2014-2015. Includes 50 color digital photographs printed on Premium Luster 13"x19" photo paper. Each image has caption written on reverse. Images #1-29 and #49 were dated 2014. Images #30-48 and #50 were dated 2015.
      From the artist's statement: "As an international student from China arriving two years ago in Durham to begin my study for a Master of Fine Arts degree at Duke, besides my clothing, I brought only my camera backpack with various digital cameras, lenses, a supply of film, and one book: Understanding Movies. At Duke I became fascinated by the fact that other international students brought with them many more items from home and I wondered about the meaning of these possessions to them. 'As a Matter of Things' features international students and the things they brought to Duke from their countries along with their own explanations of the significance of their most meaningful possessions from home."
      Any photographs used from this collection must conceal the names of the photographers.
      - As a matter of things (photographs), 2014-2015 (Box 10)
    - Polish, Mendal Diana, 2015
      Queer Home is a photographic series of 18 color photographs measuring 8.5 x 10 by Mendal Diana Polish. Polish states Queer Home "is about charting an authentic hand-made path that foregrounds the intentional building of inter-generational queer family. The initial images depict my family of origin. The images then shift into moments with my chosen family. Additional themes influencing this exhibit are home, ritual, embodiment, selfdetermination, and celebration. As a new photographer, this series was an accident. I brought the camera 'home,' to learn how to use it, and didn't even realize at first that I was telling a story, as I captured important moments that held me through this past year and a half."
      - Mom Car, CA, 2014 (Box 11)
      - San Francisco from the Roof, CA, 2014 (Box 11)
      - Thanksgiving Three, PA, 2014 (Box 11)
      - Apples, PA, 2014 (Box 11)
      - Drea, PA, 2014 (Box 11)
      - Althea Phone Tattoo, PA, 2014 (Box 11)
      - Wahzmah, PA, 2014 (Box 11)
      - Painting, PA, 2014 (Box 11)
      - Cahtleen, PA, 2014 (Box 11)
      - Sharon and Cat, PA, 2014 (Box 11)
      - Piano Family Photos, PA, 2014 (Box 11)
      - Alter, PA, 2014 (Box 11)
      - Bikes, NC, 2013 (Box 11)
      - Everyone Touching, PA, 2014 (Box 11)
      - Anais Candle Lighting, PA, 2014 (Box 11)
      - Balcony, PA, 2014 (Box 11)
      - Sue and Rachel, NC, 2013 (Box 11)
      - Qui Baby, PA, 2013 (Box 11)
    - Stanback, Windrose, 2015
      Tracing Sycamore, a MFAEDA thesis by Windrose Stanback, comprises 15 medium format color photographs printed on Innova FibaPrint Ultra Smooth Gloss 24"x24" archival paper, 1 scanned snapshot printed on Epson Ultra Premium Presentation Matte Paper 5"x7", and 2 text documents 7"x7".
      Stanback provided the following abstract: "Windrose Stanback draws from the enigmatic mist of personal memory to reimagine a fractured childhood. Centered in the dynamic realm of place and family, she uses photography to create a nurturing landscape in which to remember and reinvent the past."
      - Burst, 2015 (Box 9)
      - Them, 2015 (Box 9)
      - Story, 2015 (Box 9)
      - Sunrise, 2015 (Box 9)
      - Roots, 2015 (Box 9)
      - Rocks, 2015 (Box 9)
      - Crystals, 2015 (Box 9)
      - Ocean, 2015 (Box 9)
      - Blue, 2015 (Box 9)
      - Trunk, 2015 (Box 9)
      - Rainbow, 2015 (Box 9)
      - Misty, 2015 (Box 9)
      - Flower, 2015 (Box 9)
      - Turtle, 2015 (Box 9)
      - Pond, 2015 (Box 9)
      - Pine, 2015 (Box 9)
      - Apple, 2015 (Box 9)
      - Poem, 2015 (Box 9)
    - Striegl, Libi Rose, 2015
      Includes 1 short digital video work titled Thoroughly Known which was shown at SPECTRE Arts in Spring 2015.
      Striegl provided the following abstract: "This video is one of the generative works that served as the visual portion of libi rose striegl's MFA thesis. The video Thoroughly Known is an animated work created through manipulation of the text of the Asperger's Syndrome diagnostic description using data gathered through Natural Language Processing applications."
      - Thoroughly known, 2015, Disk image derived from optical disc. 1 video file approximately 0.4 gigabytes. (Box 12, Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0007)
    - Taalman, Alina J., 2015
      Alina Taalman's MFAEDA thesis includes one digital file of the 38 minute film "Quiet Title," and 10 artist proof prints on Hahnemuhle paper representing the larger-scale edition of prints which were shown in a solo exhibition at Spectre Arts from April 6-18th, 2015. The film screened at the Full Frame Theater and at Spectre Arts in downtown Durham as part of Alina J. Taalman's MFA thesis exhibition in Spring 2015.
      Taalman provided the following abstract: "The project Quiet Title uses the personal and the public archives to investigate a particular place across a continuum of time, drawing on traditions of documentary, experimental film and geographic research.
      'A certain tract or parcel of land, with all buildings thereon, situated Southerly of the Cemetery Road, in the town of Scotland…'
      When multiple parties claim ownership of land or property, it is said there are "clouds" on the title of the deed. Like clouds on a title, our memories are full of ambiguities and lingering attachments. The legal process for clearing clouds is referred to as a quiet title action. During this process, the disputes of all the former inhabitants need to be voiced and addressed.
      In a double exposure, time takes on a new dimension. Between the moments that each image was taken, a third element of time exists as a trace of what happened in between.
      As in memory, certain details are obscured and others are brought to the forefront, embedded in the grain.
      Satellite sensors collect energy across a wide range of the electromagnetic spectrum, and allow us to visualize the unseen. The superimposition of thermal and infrared energy along with the shorter wavelengths of the visible spectrum creates another form of double exposure."
      To all the people to whom these Presents shall come, Greeting.
      - Taalman, Alina, 2015 (Box 9)
        10 artist proof prints on Hahnemuhle paper representing the larger-scale edition of prints which were shown in a solo exhibition by Alina Taalman at Spectre Arts from April 6-18th, 2015.
      - Taalman, Alina DVD-R, 2015; Disk image derived from optical disc. 1 video file approximately 0.8 gigabytes. (Box 12, Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0007)
- MFA/EDA Theses, 2016
  Series contains Duke University Master of Fine Arts in Experimental Documentary Arts theses from the class of 2016. The projects are listed in two groups, Written Theses and Creative Theses, and within are listed in alphabetical order by the students' last names.
  - Written Theses, 2016
    This subseries contains the written theses submitted by the MFA EDA Class of 2016 whose work is part of this archive. Submission of projects to the archive is voluntary. Theses are typescripts unless otherwise noted; titles are included when known.
    - Anthony, Michael, 2016 (Box 15)
      Color Correction: A Documentary Experience
    - Baker, Kristina S., 2016 (Box 15)
      Days and Details of Death and Devils (companion book to movie, housed in Creative Thesis series).
    - Campbell, Roxanne R., 2016 (Box 15)
      Attempting Reality: A Search for Truth in Counter-Frame[s]
    - Cunningham, Alex, 2016 (Box 15)
      How To Not Find What You Weren't Really Looking For / Western Disturbances
    - Galanis, Tamika, 2016 (Box 15)
      Hacking the Narrative: Combating Erasure and the Paradisacal Myth
    - Goff, Jon-Sesrie, 2016 (Box 15)
      After Sherman: Or How To Look Back on History and Not Be Ashamed
    - Hart, Qathrin Gallaher, 2016 (Box 15)
      About a Plane Crash
    - Kim, Kihae, 2016 (Box 15)
      untitled
    - Kim, You-Jin, 2016; Four video files (MP4 format) transferred via USB drive; approximately 1.4 gigabytes. (Box 15, Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0009)
      Rain and Water. Also includes four digital video files submitted without further documentation.
    - Oppliger, Jason, 2016 (Box 15)
      The Free White Sea
    - Smith, Daniel Vincent, 2016 (Box 15)
      A Mess of Feesh
    - Thomas, Christopher, 2016 (Box 15)
      Images into Arms
    - Wang, Wei, 2016 (Box 15)
      The American Dream: An Illusion or Reality for Latino Immigrants
    - Wilkinson, Kyle Grant, 2016 (Box 15)
      middle town
  - Creative Theses, 2016
    Electronic records in this series have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact Research Services before coming to use these records.
    - Baker, Kristina, 2016
      Days and Details of Death and Devils. The collection consists of one digital file of the 50 minute film "Days and Details of Death and Devils" and a companion 306 page paperback book of the same title. Baker's abstract: "Days and Details of Death and Devils follows drug addiction in a country club community and the demise of religion in the Catholic school system juxtaposed against the rise of mental illness in one of Forbes' Multi-Year Winner for Most Miserable City in the Nation."
      - Days and details of death and devils, 2016; One MPEG-4 video file; approximately 6.0 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0007)
    - Campbell, Roxanne R., 2016; 12345 Gigabytes Forty-eight (48) items: 1. AIFF file; One(1) 7 minutes and 40 seconds; Apple ProRes 422.Mov file; One(1) 1 minutes and 49 seconds; Apple ProRes 422.Mov file; One(1) 54 seconds; Apple ProRes 422.Mov file; Three (3) promotional flyers; Two (2) Church Fans; Eighteen (18) Digital Images Tiff files; Twenty-one (21) Digital Images jpg files of photographic documentation
      The Colour Purple and other works. Campbell's abstract: "The Colour Purple Exhibition includes selections from the photographic series "The Colour Purple" and a three channel video installation "There's Just Something About Death That Makes Us Dance: the revival." The images included in this exhibition are of a two-day burial ceremony of Zion Revival Churches in the vicinity of Kingston, St. Andrews and Long Coffee, Manchester on the island of Jamaica in 2015. Both projects are auto-ethnographies, exploring themes of Creolization and religious syncretism. The exhibition is a part of a larger body of work exploring the representation of African and Afro-Caribbean culture and identity, by presenting counter frame[s] to the accepted narratives of the African diaspora in Americas."
      Campbell's thesis is closed to research until May 2021.
      - Thesis exhibition promotional flyers, and Hour Glass Church fans for "The Colour Purple," 2016, 21 JPEG image files; approximately 0.02 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0007)
      - "The Colour Purple" digital videos, 2016; Three Apple QuickTime video files; approximately 5.0 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0007)
      - "The Colour Purple" photographs, 2016; 18 TIFF image files; approximately 1.8 gigabytes. (Digital-materials RL11067-SET-0007)
    - Cunningham, Alex, 2016